<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a late abusive pamphlet, intituled, The true-born Englishman, &amp;c. Together with the true character of A true Englishman.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08373</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3304D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224705</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64550870</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 64550870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184327</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08373)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184327)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2858:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a late abusive pamphlet, intituled, The true-born Englishman, &amp;c. Together with the true character of A true Englishman.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by and for Benj. Harris, next the Golden Bear's-Head Grace-Church-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184327:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An ANSWER to a late Abuſive Pamphlet, Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The True-Born ENGLISHMAN,</hi> &amp;c. Together with the True Character of A True Engliſhman.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>A Certain <hi>Barber,</hi> fraught with much Ill Nature,</l>
               <l>Having thruſt out into the World a Satyr,</l>
               <l>Which, that he may his Reader beſt Trapan</l>
               <l>To Read, he Stiles, <hi>The True-Born Engliſhman:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wherein he goes about, with no ſmall Stir,</l>
               <l>The Character of <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> to Slur;</l>
               <l>And all their Faults in Black and White Diſplay:</l>
               <l>But if himſelf be One, as he does ſay,</l>
               <l>The Work but ill becomes him; for, at beſt,</l>
               <l>Tis a <hi>foul Bird</hi> that thus <hi>bewrayes his Nest;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And all the Odium Caſts he can deviſe,</l>
               <l>With moſt apparent Falſities and Lies,</l>
               <l>Upon his <hi>Native Country-Men:</hi> Sure he,</l>
               <l>At beſt, ſome <hi>Baſtard-Engliſhman</hi> muſt be:</l>
               <l>For none, but ſuch a One, could be ſo Baſe,</l>
               <l>To fly, like him, into his Country's Face:</l>
               <l>Peers and Plebeians he together mixes,</l>
               <l>And upon all, his Envious Venom fixes.</l>
               <l>Then, to Atone for all the Dirt he flings,</l>
               <l>A Panegyrick on King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Sings:</l>
               <l>But this, alas! is but a Feint he uſes,</l>
               <l>Whilſt he the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation thus Abuſes:</l>
               <l>We need not ſuch black Pens as his, to Sing</l>
               <l>Th' Unſully'd Glories of <hi>Great Britain's King:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>King <hi>WILLIAM's Praiſe</hi> by <hi>Engliſh Bards</hi> is Sung;</l>
               <l>With <hi>Abler Pens,</hi> and a <hi>Diviner Tongue;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For His Great Actions ſhow His Mighty Soul,</l>
               <l>Ev'n from the <hi>Arctick,</hi> to th' <hi>Antarctick</hi> Pole.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> maugre what He can ſay,</l>
               <l>King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Love, and Honour, and Obey;</l>
               <l>And do as much His Royal Title Own,</l>
               <l>As any Monarch's e'er poſſeſs'd the Throne.</l>
               <l>And therefore, that the World may plainly ſee</l>
               <l>How very much unlike the <hi>Engliſh</hi> be,</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:184327:2"/>
               <l>To what he repreſents them, I have here</l>
               <l>Set down in Brief their proper Character:</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The True-Engliſhman.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE <hi>Free-Born Engliſh, Generous</hi> and <hi>Wiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hate <hi>Chains,</hi> yet do not <hi>Government</hi> Deſpiſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>Crown, Tribute</hi> and <hi>Taxes</hi> They,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Lawfully Exacted,</hi> Freely Pay;</l>
                  <l>Which cannot be, but by their <hi>own Conſent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And given in a <hi>Free-Choſe Parliament:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Force</hi> they <hi>Abhor,</hi> and <hi>Wrongs</hi> they <hi>Scorn to Bear;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to Aſſert their <hi>Rights</hi> they always Dare.</l>
                  <l>More guided by their <hi>Judgment</hi> than their <hi>Fear:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juſtice</hi> by them was never held <hi>Severe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Pow'r</hi> by <hi>Tyranny</hi> was never got:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laws</hi> may perhaps <hi>inſlave them, Force</hi> cannot:</l>
                  <l>Nor can their Freedom be by <hi>Laws</hi> Deſtroy'd,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Laws</hi> 'gainſt <hi>Magna Charta</hi> ſtill are <hi>Void:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They therefore know (ſhou'd they be thus Betray'd)</l>
                  <l>Laws that are <hi>Void,</hi> are not to be <hi>Obey'd:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Kings are leſs Safe, in their <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbounded Will,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Joyn'd with the <hi>Wretched Pow'r</hi> of <hi>Doing Ill:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Forſaken most,</hi> when they're <hi>most Abſolute:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Laws GUARD the Man, and only BIND the Brute.</l>
                  <l>To force that Guard with its worſt <hi>Foe</hi> to Joyn,</l>
                  <l>Can never be a <hi>Prudent King</hi>'s Deſign:</l>
                  <l>What Prince would change to be a <hi>Cataline?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Break his own Laws, ſhake the Unqueſtion'd Throne;</l>
                  <l>Contpire with Vaſſals to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p his Own?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let <hi>France</hi> grow Proud beneath the Tyrant's Luſt,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt the Wrac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d People Crawl, and lick the Duſt:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Mighty Genius</hi> of this Iſle Diſdains</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>High-ſhoon Slavery,</hi> and <hi>Golden Chains.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>England</hi> to Servile Yoke cou'd never Bow:</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Conq'rours</hi> ne'er Preſum'd, who dares do now?</l>
                  <l>In vain <hi>Rome</hi>'s Biſhop then does Wrack his Brain;</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prince can in this Iſland Reign.</l>
                  <l>Though <hi>Spain</hi> be added to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It will their Courage, not their Fear, Enhance.</l>
                  <l>Arm'd with <hi>Blest Bibles,</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndated Law,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They'll <hi>guard Themſelves,</hi> and <hi>keep the World in Awe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And 'tis their Honour, <hi>Europe</hi> now muſt wait,</l>
                  <l>And from their <hi>Great Reſolves,</hi> Receive its Fate.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printedby, and for <hi>Benj. Harris,</hi> next the Golden <hi>Boar's-Head, Grace-Church-Street,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
